Finding aid for the Karl G. Yoneda papers, 1892-1998, bulk 1925-1989 LSC.1592
UCLA Library Special Collections
Karl G. Yoneda papers
1892-1998, bulk 1925-1989
1925-1989
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yoneda, Karl G., 1906-1999
LSC.1592
23 Linear Feet (46 document boxes, 1 map folder)
Karl G. Yoneda was a Kibei-nisei, born in Glendale, California in 1906 and stayed in Japan between 1913 and 1926. He returned to the United States in 1927 and joined the American Communist Party. During World War II, Yoneda was incarcerated in the Manzanar War Relocation Center and volunteered to join the Military Intelligence Service Language School from the camp. He served for the China-Burma-India Theater as a member of the Psychological Warfare Team, the United States Office of War Information. Starting in the late 1960s, Yoneda gave lectures and talks at various classes and programs of academic institutions in the West Coast and Hawaii and authored publications in English and Japanese. The collection consists of materials related to Yoneda's involvement in the Japanese American left and labor movement, World War II internment, and the United States Military services. Includes original manuscripts, publications, correspondence, photographs, and photocopied testimonies and investigation case files.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu. Includes: one CD-R, 700 MB storage capacity
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Karl G. Yoneda, 1990.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9936493453606533
Biography/History
Karl G. Yoneda was born in Glendale, California in 1906 to Japanese immigrant parents. Because of his father's illness, the Yoneda family left the United States for Japan in 1913. During his stay in Japan, Yoneda received his education and was influenced by left-wing and socialist ideas. Escaping from Japanese conscription, he returned alone to the United States in 1926. In the United States he joined the American Communist Party, which launched his career as a labor and union organizer. As a longshoreman by trade, he was affiliated with the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU), and also served as the vice president and delegate of the Congress of Industrial Organizations Alaskan Cannery Workers Union. He was an editor of ???? Rodo Shinbun [= Japanese labor news] in San Francisco, an official newspaper of the Japanese section of the American Communist Party, and a contributor to ?? Doho, a Japanese American leftist newspaper (a broad united front progressive paper) published in Los Angeles. He was also a poet, publishing poems under several pseudonyms.
During World War II, Yoneda and his wife, Elaine Black Yoneda, were interned in the Manzanar War Relocation Center in Independence, California. During incarceration, he served as a block manager and also formed the Manzanar Citizens Federation, which consisted of pro-American and pro-communist internees. Its purpose was to improve camp conditions, initiate leadership education, participate in war efforts, and prepare evacuees for postwar life. In the camp, he volunteered to join the Military Intelligence Service Language School and was enlisted in the Psychological Warfare Team, the United States Office of War Information (OWI), and served for the China-Burma-India Theater.
Starting in the late 1960s, Yoneda gave lectures and talks in various classes and programs of academic institutions on the West Coast and in Hawaii. He also authored publications in English and Japanese. In 1999, Yoneda passed away at age 92 in Fort Bragg, California.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to Karl Yoneda's involvement in the Japanese American left and labor movement, World War II internment, and the United States Military services. It includes original manuscripts, publications, correspondence, photographs, and photocopied testimonies and investigation case files. Of note are leaflets and newspapers published and distributed by the Japanese Bureau of the American Communist Party, leftist groups, and labor union members between 1923 and 1939. The materials were distributed among Japanese communities in California, Seattle, Alaska, New York, Hawaii, Canada, Japan, and Shanghai for various purposes, including to call for community participation internationally in the political fight against Japanese imperialism and in the support of communists and the Soviet Union, and to advocate improvement of working conditions and higher wages of local labor workers in California.
The collection also contains materials related to the internment of Yoneda and his wife, Elaine Black Yoneda, in the Manzanar War Relocation Center. Materials Yoneda collected immediately following the attack on Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941 depict the anti-Japanese sentiment in the United States, while the materials written by Yoneda and/or the Japanese American community groups express their faithful allegiance to the United States. During incarceration, Yoneda served as a block manager as well as a member of the Manzanar Citizens Federation; as a result, this collection also contains Yoneda's reports and letters describing the camp conditions, its organization and administration structure, jobs and wages, activities, and programs.
Propaganda materials included in the collection consist of ?? dentan [= airborne leaflets], newspapers, pamphlets, and a military song book produced by the United States Psychological Warfare Team, Office of War Information. The purpose of propaganda materials was to call on Japanese soldiers to surrender in the China-Burma-India Theater between 1944 and 1945.
Most of the collection is written in English and Japanese; some Japanese texts are attached with an English synopsis and annotations. A small portion of materials are written in Chinese, Korean, Burmese, and Russian.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Communist/Labor Union Activities
World War II Internment
Military Service of Japanese Americans
Manuscripts, Publications, and Lectures
Japanese American/Canadian Redress and Reparations
Investigation Case Files
Japanese American Citizens League
Correspondence
Personal Memorabilia
Political Subject Files
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Journalists -- United States -- Archives.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Alaska Cannery Workers Association; Communist Party of the United States of America; Manzanar War Relocation Center; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union; Military Intelligence Service Language School (U.S.); United States. Office of War Information.; Yoneda, Karl G., 1906-1999
- 1. Communist and Labor Union Activities, 1909-1993
  Scope and Contents note
  Series comprises materials regarding Yoneda's activities as a communist and labor union member. Included are his membership materials, communist and socialist publications, such as leaflets, brochures, periodicals, and monographs published mostly between 1923 and 1942, photographs of events and incidents, meeting minutes, news clippings, and others. There are also folders containing materials regarding Yoneda's activities as a member of the Alaskan Cannery Workers Union, the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, and the American Communist Party.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  Includes: one CD-R, 700 MB storage capacity
  - 1.1. Membership, 1927-1992 bulk 1927-1979
    Yoneda's membership cards, work books, strike cards, identification cards, a press card, and certificates issued by various labor unions and workers groups mainly in San Francisco and Los Angeles, California, between 1927 and 1979. Also includes other identifications and cards, driver's license, and permits. Consists of mainly original items; some items are available in photocopy format only.
    - Membership Cards, 1927-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Various labor unions and workers' groups include: Agricultural Workers Industrial League affiliated with the Trade Union Unity League; American Federation of Labor; Alaska Cannery Workers Union; Cannery Workers Union; Workers (Communist) Party of America; Communist Party USA, New York; ?? Doho; International Longshoremen's Association; International Labor Defense; International Longshoremen's & Warehousemen's Union; Japanese Restaurant Worker's Union of Los Angeles; League of Struggle for Negro Rights New York City; ??????? Nihonjin Rodo Kyokai = Japanese Worker's Association; ?????????? Nihonjin Noen Rodosha Kumiai = Japanese Agricultural Workers Union; Pacific Coast Fisheries Organization and Coordinate Committee United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America, an affiliate of the C.I.O.; Pacific Maritime Association; Sonoma County Poultry Growers Association; The Southwest Labor Studies Association; and Unemployed Council affiliated with the Trade Union Unity League.
    - Certification Letters, 1934-1936, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Certificates of Yoneda's membership issued by Japanese Workers Association; Pan-Pacific Trade Union Secretariat; San Francisco Bay Area District Council No. 2 Maritime Federation of the Pacific Coast; and the Unity of the International Working Class.
  - 1.2. Political Events and Incidents, 1931-1936, 1953-1956, 1964-1977
    Contains materials regarding political events and incidents in which Yoneda was involved. Includes a workers' event calendar recording the political events in 1933; photographs capturing Yoneda's participation in political events in 1931, and between 1971 and 1972; materials filed by particular events and incidents that took place in 1930s, containing letters, photographs, news clippings, and others.
    - Workers' Event Calendar, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      A 1933 calendar recording workers events. In English and Japanese.
    - Photographs, 1931-1936, 1960, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Four black and white photographs of Karl and Elaine Yoneda participating in political activities in 1931-1936, 1960, and 1971-1973: The Free Tom Mooney/Kentucky Harlan Miners/Scottsboro Nine Conference in Long Beach, California, on October 4, 1931; the hunger march to the unemployed state convention in San Francisco, California, on January 11, 1931; the World Conference Against A-H Bombs, Tokyo, Japan, on August 5, 1960; the 1971-1972 Longshoremen strike picket line, San Francisco, California; the World Peace Congress, Moscow, on October 26, 1973; and one unknown event on August 8, 1936. Also includes a portrait of Karl and Elaine Yoneda taken in March 1933.
    - Communist Party Nomination, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Materials regarding Yoneda's nomination as a candidate for the office of member of assembly, 22nd assembly district, the Communist Party at the primary election on August 28, 1934. Includes a certificate of nomination issued by Office of Secretary of State, Sacramento, California; a letter issued by the State of California, Department of State; a photograph of Yoneda; and photocopies of news clippings and leaflets featuring Yoneda's candidacy.
    - Los Angeles "Red Squad" Incidents, 1931, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Materials regarding two incidents of Los Angeles "Red Squad" in 1931 and 1938. Yoneda was arrested by the "Red Squad" during a hunger march in Los Angeles, on February 10, 1931. Los Angeles "Red Squad" led by Captain Hynes raided a "Japan Night", an event sponsored by ???? Rodo Shinbun, Japanese Proletarian Cultural League, and International Labor Defense, at the Hollywood John Reed Club on February 11, 1933. Includes photographs of Yoneda after released on bail and the scene of the Hollywood John Reed Club, and news clippings.
    - Political Deportation Cases, 1953, 1956, 1964-1965, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Documents regarding Japanese political deportees caused by the Long Beach incident in 1932, deporting nine Japanese members of the Communist Party, USA. and other deportees leaving for the Soviet Union, between 1931 and 1935. Also includes materials regarding deportees as a result of the Walter McCarrran act in 1956, arresting allegedly illegal aliens on charges of their past membership with the Communist Party.
    - Nichi-Bei Strikes in 1931 and 1938, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Strikes against the Nichi-Bei, a Japanese newspaper press, in San Francisco, California, in 1931 and 1938. Includes chronologies compiled by Yoneda in 1970, his notes, photographs of the 1931 strike leaders, and a photocopy of a news clipping.
    - U.S. Café Chain Restaurant Strikes in 1930s, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Leaflets, news clippings, bulletins regarding the Los Angeles U.S. Cafés' strikes and labor disputes in the 1930s. Includes correspondence; research notes on Thomas G. Toyama; a retainer agreement for attorneys' fees signed by Yoneda; and news clippings. The correspondence includes letters from attorneys, James A. Miller and Neil Gotanda, copies of Yoneda's letters to the Rafu Shinpo editor to correct the newspaper article about the 1974 Horikawa Strike in Little Tokyo, and letters to Kikue and Shuji Fujii.
  - 1.3. Leaflets and Brochures, 1923-1939
    Leaflets and brochures published by communists, labor union members, and leftists groups, including ??? Dohosha, ????? Rodo Shinbunsha, ??????? Zaibei Okinawa Seinenkai, ?????????? Kaiho Undo Giseisha Kyuenkai, ??????? Kokusai Sekishoku Kyuenkai, and Proletarian groups in Los Angeles, San Francisco, other areas in California, Seattle, Alaska, New York, Hawaii, Canada, Japan, and Shanghai, China, between 1923 and 1939. The materials were distributed among the Japanese communities to call for community participation internationally in the political fight against Japanese imperialism and in the support of communists and the Soviet Union, and advocating improvement of local working conditions and a higher wage for labor workers in California. The materials are predominantly in English and Japanese, with some in Chinese; English translation texts are attached to some of Japanese leaflets. All files are arranged by publication location.
    - Manuscripts of Leaflets in Los Angeles, California, 1929 March 23, 1929 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Two manuscripts of leaflets written by: ?????????????? Zenbei Nihonjin Rodo Kyokai Daihyosha Kaigi [= Japanese Workers Association of America Representatives Council]; and ??????????????? Zai Rafu Nihonjin Dato Tanaka Naikaku Koenkai. In Japanese.
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1925-1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1935-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in San Francisco, California, 1923-1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in San Francisco, California, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in San Francisco, California, 1936-1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Sacramento, Oakley, Tulare, Stockton, Lodi, and Walnut Grove, California, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in New York, 1929-1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Seattle and Alaska, 1929-1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Hawaii, 1928-1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Vancouver, Canada, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Manuscripts of Leaflets and Brochures in Japan, circa 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Leaflets and Brochures Published and Distributed in Japan and Shanghai, 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1.4. Periodicals, 1911-1975, bulk 1925-1937
    Periodicals, including bulletins, newspapers, and newsletters, issued and distributed by communist, socialist, and other political groups in United States, Canada, China, Vladivostok, and Japan, in 1911, between 1923 and 1942, 1945, 1946, and between 1954 and 1975. Also includes collection of news clippings. The materials are in Japanese and English; and arranged by publication location.
    - ?????·?????·???? Nashonaru Byuro Buruten = National Buro Bulletin. [United States], 1929 November-1930 March (Box 2, Folder 11)
      ?????·?????·???? Nashonaru Byuro Buruten = National Buro Bulletin. [United States]: Japanese Buro, Communist Party, USA. V.1-2 (Nov.-Dec. 1929), v.4 (Mar. 1930).
    - ???? To Kensetsusha = Party Builder. [United States], 1932 August, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      ???? To Kensetsusha = Party Builder. [United States]: Kokusai Kyosanto Nihon Shibu Kyosanto Chuo Iinkai. V. 1, no. 2 (Aug. 29, 1932); [United States]: Kokusai Kyosanto Shibu Beikoku Kyosanto Chuo Iinkai Nihongo Shokikyoku. V. 1, no. 1 (June 10, 1935)-no. 2 (Dec. 10, 1935), v. 2, no. 1 (Jan. 10, 1936)-no. 4 (Nov. 29, 1936), v. [3], no. 5 (July, 1937), v. [3], no. 8 (Oct., 1937)-no. 9 (Nov., 1937) and 1938.
    - ?????? Kyuen Buriten; ?????? Kyuen Nyusu; ???? Kyuen no Tomo = Friend of the I.L.D. Los Angeles, California, 1930-1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      ?????? Kyuen Buriten. Los Angeles: International Labor Defense Nihonjin Shibu. Oct., 1930-Dec., 1931; ?????? Kyuen Nyusu. Los Angeles: Kokusai Rodosha Kyuenkai Horiuchi Shibu. No. 4 (July, 1931), no. 7 (Jan., 1932); ???? Kyuen no Tomo = Friend of the I.L.D. Los Angeles: Kokusai Rodo Yogo Renmei Rafu-ku Sano Manabu Shibu. No. 1 (Mar., 1934)-no. 2 (Apr., 1934), no. 6 (Feb., 1934).
    - ??? Hataraku Hito. Los Angeles, California, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      ??? Hataraku Hito. Los Angeles: Nanka Puroretaria Bunka Domei. No. [1] (May/June, 1933), no. 11 (Aug., 1934), no. 14 (Nov., 1934)-no. 18 (May, 1935).
    - ?? Densha. Beverly Hills, California, 1937 April (Box 3, Folder 2)
      ?? Densha. Beverly Hills: Romey Yamashita. No. [1] (Apr., 1937).
    - Twelve Periodicals Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      ???? Shitamachi Tsushin. No. [1] (Aug. 15, 1935); ????????????????? Shokuryohin Sangyo Rodosha Resutoranto Jugyoin = Restaurant Employees. No. 1 (Jan. 30, 1934)-no. 2 (Feb. 28, 1934); ???????? ? Sutoraiki Nyusu = Strike News. No. 1 (Mar. 18, 1934)-no. 3 (Mar. 20, 1934); ??????????? Noen Sutoraiki Nyusu = Agricultural Strike News. No. 1 (May 3, 1936)-no. 2 (May 13, 1936), no. 4 (May 25, 1936), no. 6 (May 25, 1936)-no. 9 (June 14, 1936); ?????????? Gekkan Noen Rodosha Nankaban = Monthly Agricultural Worker, Southern California Edition. No. 1 (May 1, 1934); ???? Nisei no Koe. V. 1, no. 2 (Nov., 1933)-no. 3 (Dec., 1933); ???????? ·???·???? Maketto Ranku Ando Fairu = Market Rank & File. V. 1, no. 1 (May, 1937)-no.3 (Aug. 1937), no.5 (May 19, 1937); Market Rank & File. No. 2 (July 27, [1937?]), no. 4 (July 31, [1937?]), no. 7 (Aug. 7, 1937); ???????? ??? Furutsu Sutando Jugyoin. v. [1], no. [1] (Jan. 15, 1933), v. 1, no. 2 (1933); ??????? Gadena no Tomo. No. 2 (1934); ???? Musan Taishu = The Musan Taishu. No. 2 (Apr. 1, 1934); and The Market Worker. V. 1, no. 2 (Apr. 1, 1937).
    - Four Periodicals Published and Distributed in Los Angeles, California, 1933-1935, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Items are stored in Box 47 (oversize).
    - ?? Zenshin. Los Angeles, California, 1937 January 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      ?? Zenshin. Los Angeles: Henri Sugimura. No. 1 (Jan. 1, 1937). In Japanese.
    - ?? Doho = Doho. Los Angeles, California, 1937 February 1-1939 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      ?? Doho = Doho. Los Angeles: Dohosha. No. 2 (Feb. 1, 1937)-no. 3 (Mar. 1, 1937), no. 5 (May 1, 1937)-no. 6 (June 1, 1937), no. 9 (Oct. 15, 1937)-no. 15 (Apr. 10, 1938), no. 17 (May 21, 1938)-no. 18 (June 10, 1938), no. 20 (Aug. 1, 1938), no. 22 (Sept. 15, 1938)-no. 42 (July 15, 1939), no. 44 (Aug. 15, 1939)-no. 52 (Dec. 15, 1939). No. 2-3, 5-6, 9-15, 17-18 are published in Japanese only; no. 20, 22-42, 44-52 in Japanese and English.
    - ?? Doho = Doho. Los Angeles, California, 1940 February 15-1941 November 25 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      ?? Doho = Doho. Los Angeles: Dohosha. No. 56 (Feb. 15, 1940), no. 58 (Mar. 15, 1940), no. 60 (May 1, 1940), no. 65 (July. 15, 1940), no. 73 (Nov. 15, 1940), no. 75 (Dec. 15, 1940)-no. 86 (June 1, 1941), no. 88 (July 1, 1941)-no. 100 (Nov. 25, 1941). In Japanese and English.
    - ?? Doho = Doho. Los Angeles, California, 1942 February 15-March 13, 1942 April 23-May 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      ?? Doho = Doho. Los Angeles: Dohosha. No. 109 (Feb. 15, 1942)-no. 120 (Mar. 13, 1942), no. 127 (Apr. 23, 1942)-no. 128 (May 4, 1942). In Japanese and English.
    - Doho: San Francisco Supplement. San Francisco, California, 1941 December 13-22 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - ??? = Kaikyusen. San Francisco, California, 1926 September 5-1928 January 5 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - ?????? Soko Taimusu = Soko Times. San Francisco, California, 1935 May 30-1936 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      ?????? Soko Taimusu = Soko Times. San Francisco: Kyosanto Soko Nihongohan = Unit 2, Fillmore Section, Communist Party, USA. No. 1 (May 30, 1935)-no. 25 (June 25, 1936), three issues of special edition. Publisher changed to Soko Times Sha from no. 17 (Jan. 1, 1936); Editor: Karl Hama (=Karl Yoneda).
    - Japan Letter. San Francisco, California, 1954 January (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Japan Letter. San Francisco: San Francisco Kibei Group. V. 1, no. 1 (Jan. 1954). Chief editor: Mike Masato Deguchi. In English.
    - ???? Kyuen no Tomo. San Francisco, California, 1934-1935 October (Box 4, Folder 1)
      ???? Kyuen no Tomo. San Francisco: International Labor Defense Nagura Branch. No. [1] (Oct., 1934)-no. 4 (1935). In Japanese.
    - ?????? Zaibei Rodo Shinbun = The Japanese Worker in America. San Francisco, California, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco, California, 1930 January 10-December 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco: Rodo Shinbunsha. No. 35 (Jan. 10, 1930)-no. 46 (July 25, 1930), no. 49 (Sept. 25, 1930)-no.53 (Dec. 10, 1930). In Japanese.
    - ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco, California, 1931 January 10-December 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco: Rodo Shinbunsha. No. 54 (Jan. 10, 1931)-no. 58 (Mar. 25, 1931), no. 60 (May 1, 1931)-no. 68 (Oct. 15, 1931), no. 70 (Nov. 15, 1931)-no. 71 (Dec. 1, 1931). In Japanese.
    - ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco, California, 1932 January 1-December 25 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco: Rodo Shinbunsha. No. 72 (Jan. 1, 1932)-no. 88 (Dec. 25, 1932). In Japanese.
    - ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco, California, 1933 January 5-December 31 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      ???? Rodo Shinbun. San Francisco: Rodo Shinbunsha. No. 89 (Jan. 5, 1933)-no. 113 (Dec. 31, 1933). In Japanese.